<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Payre of two mornings meditations the first against parity.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56180</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12448</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12538330</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12538330</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62898</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56180)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62898)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 946:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Payre of two mornings meditations the first against parity.</title>
                  <author>A. P.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: A.P.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Divine right of kings.</term>
               <term>Monarchy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="section">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62898:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Payre</hi> OF TWO MORNINGS MEDITATIONS. <hi>The firſt againſt</hi> Parity. <hi>Sect.</hi> I.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough Men by Nature are equall, yet ſo it is, that being borne to live in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, and this ſociety not being able to ſubſiſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out peace, peace without union, union without or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r, order without diſtinction, diſtinction with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t dependency, or dependency without autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62898:2"/> yet the ſame Nature which made men equall (in one reſpect) hath immediatly commanded them to be ſubject to one head, and to wave their equality, for the avoyding of confuſion. GOD himſelfe in the Creation framed not many men at once, who might the ſooner have ſtored the Earth: he made but one Man onely: yea ſo, as that he made not Man and VVoman together of Earth: but firſt drew one Man from the Earth, and extracted one VVoman, from that only one Man: to ſhew, (as St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> divinely no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth) how his intention was to eſtabliſh Deriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Dependency, Domination, Principality, yea and Monarchy among men, and to reduce them all under one Root and Superiour, cauſing them all to proceede from one onely, to the end all might depend upon one. He ever ſince, hath at all times inſtituted Temporall Princes and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers over his choſen people: firſt Patriarchs, then Dukes, after this Iudges, and in concluſion Kings. His Providenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> concluding in Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, (calling himſelfe by the ſtile and name of King) as the chiefeſt higheſt title, and the moſt perfect forme of Governement. As Nature
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62898:2"/> which proceedeth by degrees in her workes, firſt maketh Mercury out of the vapours of the Earth, after, out of Mercury, ſilver, and out of ſilver, gold, the crowne and perfection of all Mettals: ſo IESVS CHRIST comming (af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the VVorld, (albeit he was Lord and King of Kings, of Heaven and Earth) hath (by his word, as example) confirmed temporall policy and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, commanding to give unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> what is due to <hi>Caeſar:</hi> And the Apoſtle enjoineth us, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der paine of eternall damnation, to yeeld to our temporall Sovereignes, Obedience, Tribute, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, Honour, and our Prayers, becauſe hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends our lives and goods from violence: Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, ſince he derives his power from GOD: Reſpect, in that he is his Miniſter: Honour, by reaſon he beareth his Image: Prayers, in refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to, and upon, the great neede hee hath of GODS aſſiſtance in defending us. Divine and Evangelicall Law obligeth us, to yeeld him all theſe duties. Obedience, in regard of his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: Tribute, to defray his great charges: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, in regard of his Miniſtry: Honour, for his dignity: Prayers, for his neceſſities.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Ita dicit, ut ſencit.</hi> A.P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="section">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:62898:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Second</hi> Againſt prepoſterous and irregular COUNSELLS. <hi>Sect.</hi> II.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL the true good of Man, both particular and publicke, depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth upon the ſafe conduct of good Counſells, good Counſells on true wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and this true wiſedome
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62898:3"/> on GOD. Now ſince (according to Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicall maximes) one cannot deliver an aſſured judgement of things, but in conſidering the refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, relation, and connexion they have with primary cauſes: God, therefore, who is this firſt cauſe, ought to be the primary object, and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall rule of all our judgements and counſells, if we deſire to ſecure our judgements from errour, and our counſells from temerity. For, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver men have, at any time, eſtabliſhed of good or juſt in temporall Laws, either imprinted in them by nature, or deduced by reaſon, or knowne by inſpiration, or manifeſted by revelation, if it ſtray from this principle, it is unjuſt, and what is unjuſt is violent, and what is violent cannot chalenge the name of Law. For this is the moſt ſolid ground of the moſt eminent commendations wee can give to the truly wiſe Politician, who, over and above the naturall capacity of ſpirit, and of humane wiſedome acquired by ſtudy, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of affaires, addeth divine knowledge, which he taketh as the principall guide of all his moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, reaſons, maximes, counſells, decrees, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. He doth not (as the Lesbian builders)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62898:4"/> fit his ſquire or rule to the ſtone or timber, as they doe who ſeeke to accommodate God to their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities and affaires, or juſtice to the times, but he fitteth and faſhioneth the timber and ſtones to the ſquire or ruler, affaires and neceſſities to God, and the times to Iuſtice. He imitateth good Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, who holding the hand on the helme, lift up their eyes to heaven, to receive from the Pole and ſtarres the conduct of themſelves and ſhips: for whileſt he manageth the ſteering of Civill affairs, he hath his eyes fixed on eternall verities, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the divine Law, whence he taketh his <hi>notions, levy,</hi> and directions. And as the High-Prieſt of the old Law, drew the anſwers and oracles he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the people, from a pretious ſtone hee carried on his breaſt, which in a marvellous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner (as ſome have delivered) repreſented unto him Gods pleaſure by its colour, ſometimes red, at another time blacke; one while pale, then white, then changeable, according to occurrents: In like manner, the true wiſe man, taketh his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells and reſolutions from Gods Law, <hi>A Pretious Topace</hi> (as <hi>David</hi> termeth it) not hung at his breaſt, but faſtned to his heatt, <hi>Oh God, I have hid thy
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62898:4"/> words in mine heart,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.11.127. There doth he finde (in eternall reaſons) the true rule of things paſſed in all ſeaſons, and contemplateth in immoveable verities, the conſtant IDEA of whatſoever is ſubject to change and revolution; whence taking his meaſures, he (after, or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after) guideth the inconſtant by the conſtant, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it to ſlide into ſtability, the temporall by the eternall, the figure of the world (which paſſeth) by Gods Truth, which is eternally permanent.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Dixi. A.</hi> P.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:62898:5"/>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>Exod. 28.17.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="3">Row 1.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sardus</hi> 6.</cell>
                     <cell rows="3">2</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Emeraud</hi> 4.</cell>
                     <cell rows="3">3</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Ligute.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="3">4</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Beril</hi> 8.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Topaz</hi> 9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Saphir</hi> 2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Agate.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Onyx.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Carbuncle</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Diamond.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Amethyſt</hi> 12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Jaſpar</hi> 1.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell cols="3">Revelat. 21.19, 20.</cell>
                     <cell cols="2">Alphabeticall order.</cell>
                     <cell cols="3">Alphabeticall order.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="13">Foundation.</cell>
                     <cell>1. <hi>Jaſpar</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Amethyſt</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Agate</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>0.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. <hi>Saphir</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Beril</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>8.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Amethyſt</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>12.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3. <hi>Chalcidonie.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Chalcidonie</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Beril</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>8.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4. <hi>Emerald</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Chryſopraſus</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Carbuncle</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>0.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5. <hi>Sardonix.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Chryſolite</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>7.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Diamond</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>0.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6. <hi>Sardius</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Emerald</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Emeraud</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7. <hi>Chryſolite.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Jacinct</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>11.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Jaſpar</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8. <hi>Beril</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Jaſpar</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Ligute</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>0.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9. <hi>Topas</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Saphir</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Onyx</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>0.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>10. <hi>Chryſopraſus.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sardius</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Saphir</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>2.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>11. <hi>Jacinct.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sardonix</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sardius</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>6.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>12. <hi>Amethyſt</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Topas</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Topaz</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>9.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell cols="2">Rows</cell>
                     <cell cols="2">Foundations.</cell>
                     <cell cols="3">Rows. Foundations.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell cols="4">
                        <hi>Perme A. P.</hi> 8.20.44.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
